麦克
Mike.
麦克，我在打电话
Mike, I'm trying to talk on the phone.
对不起，我没注意到
Right. I didn't even notice, Carol. Sorry.
太棒了
Neat!
麦克!
Michael!
孩子们
Hi, guys.
爸爸，下午好
Good afternoon, Father.
今天发零用钱
Oh, it's allowance day.
是吗？
- It is? - Oh?
我都忘了
What do you know?
你们装得挺像的
You kids really think you can con me.
爸爸，我在清洁，没听到你说什么
I'm sorry, Father, I couldn't hear you. I was dusting.
好吧，给你们血汗钱
Please. Okay. Here's your blood money.
好的
All right.
这不代表你们骗得过我了
Just don't think for a minute I bought into your act...
不过谢谢你们这样大费周章
and thanks for going to the trouble of trying to deceive me.
随时乐意
Anytime.
另外，我也不介意.
And it warms my heart...
在妈妈回来以前.
to know that this room will be clean...
你们能把这里打扫干净，叠好衣服
and the laundry neatly folded by the time your mom gets home.
爸，你给多了
Hey, Dad, you gave me too much...
我也是，双倍
Me, too. He gave me double.
我也是，这不妥
Yeah, me, too. Hey, I don't like this.
事有蹊跷
Something smells rotten.
是本
It's Ben.
现在是二月份，忘了吗？
No, it's February. Remember?
爸爸的生日骗局
Yeah, it's Dad's annual birthday scam.
老头要让我们把零用钱都买礼物
The old man thinks he's going to con us into spending all this on him.
真可怜
Poor guy.
-凯罗，你买什么礼物？ -我不说
- So, Carol, what are you going to get him? - I'm not telling.
又送汗衫，一如往年？
What, another preppy shirt like you get him every year?
我能怎么超越你呢？
How, oh, how, will I ever top that?
我要送他最好的礼物
Well, I've got the perfect present.
是什么？
What?
我在学校做的烟灰缸
I'm giving Dad the ashtray I created in school.
他不抽烟，你想得真周到
Great present for a guy who doesn't smoke.
那你送他什么礼物？
Yeah, well, what are you going to get him?
-准备好了吗？ -好
- All right, you guys ready for this? - Sure.
-送一本书 -爸爸有很多书了
- A book. - Dad already has a book.
天哪，那倒是
Oh, my God, that's right.
(English Subtitle) Growing.Pains.S01E17 -= Charity.Begins.at.Home =- Subripped by zerox
★祝我生日快乐，祝我生日快乐
I wish me a happy birthday I wish me a happy birthday
★祝我生日快乐
I wish me a happy birthday
★因为我是好样的
'Cause I'm such a cool guy
-亲爱的 -亲爱的
- Hi, sweetheart. - Hi, honey.
今天好吗？
How was your day?
妙手回春的心理医师.
My day. Listen, the old miracle-worker here had a major breakthrough...
在一个治疗两年的病人上有了突破
with a patient I've been treating for two years now.
吸尘器的声音？
Is that the vacuum cleaner?
对，孩子们在打扫
Yeah. Yeah, the kids are cleaning.
-病人已经.. -全部都在？
- So, anyway, this patient... - All of them?
对，让我说说那个.
Yeah. So let me tell you about this guy.
恐惧自己体液的病人.
Now, he was terrified of his own bodily fluids...
你是怎么让他们打扫的？
How did you get them to do it?
我是个高明的外交家
I'm a master communicator.
-你今天好吗？ -不错
- So how was your day? - Fair.
病人没什么进展？
Nothing exciting happened with any of your patients?
没，没，没
No, no, no.
-今天过得好吗？ -好极了
- So how was your day? - Fantastic.
弗瑞德把我叫到办公室.
Fred Mathis called me into his office...
要我连载一个星期
and assigned me an entire series for next week.
是吗？
Really?
"Let's get serious about raw sewage."
哇!
Wow!
真是兴奋
I'm so excited.
你不是报道过污水的事吗？
Didn't you already do a story about waste?
人们看到污水就会想到我
Well, I guess when they think of sewage, they think of me.
我这个周末一定会很忙
So, anyway, I'm really going to have my hands full this weekend.
周末？
This weekend?
-星期六？ -对
- Saturday? - Yep.
2月8号？
February the 8th?
对，有什么安排吗？
Yes. Why? Do we have plans I don't know about?
没什么，对某个人来说很重要
No, unless it just might be a special day for someone.
好吧
Oh, that's right.
我又怎会忘记呢？
How could I have forgotten?
是总统纪念日
Presidents' Day.
甜心，今天过得好吗？
So how was your day, sweetheart?
好吧，若是我们省着用.
All right now, Carol, if we both keep our heads...
也许够钱买汗衫做生日礼物
we can get through this birthday without losing our shirts.
不好意思，买什么礼物都说出来了
I'm sorry. I didn't mean to mention shirts, Carol.
你打算花多少钱？
So how much you spending?
不知道，你打算花多少？
I don't know. How much you gonna spend?
-需要多少就多少 -不能超过10块
- As much as it takes. - Okay, but not over $10.
10块？我一星期才2块
$10? I only get $2 a week.
好吧，10块差不多了
Okay, I can live with $10.
这应该不包括贺卡吧？
Of course, with a card it might cost a little more.
-不是说好10块吗？ -凯罗
- Did I say $10? - Carol.
-12块 -12块半
- $12. - $12.50.
-麦克 -好吧，11块
- Mike. - All right, all right. $11.
-15块 -凯罗
- $15. - Carol.
好吧，25块
All right, okay. $25.
肯定不是情人节
Now, I know it's not Valentine's Day.
那是2月14号
That's the 14th.
算了吧
I said never mind.
杰森，给我提示
Come on, Jason, give me a hint.
我提示就没意思了
No, if I have to do that, it ruins it.
小宝贝
Hi, punkinhead.
本，你来得正好
Well, Ben. You're just in time.
提醒妈妈星期六是什么日子
Would you please remind your mother exactly what Saturday is?
-土拔鼠节？ -算了
- Groundhog's Day? - That does it.
我还是回办公室吧.
I'm going to my office where people not only appreciate me...
同事在我生日那天会点蜡烛
they light candles on the day I was born.
17年了，他还以为我会忘记他的生日
You'd think after 17 years, he'd know that I wouldn't forget his birthday.
本，你们把衣服.
Wow, Ben. You folded this all by your...
谁在上面流口水了？
Who drooled all over the laundry?
-妈，有空吗？ -有啊
- You got a minute, Mom? - Sure, honey.
我没钱给爸爸买一份好的礼物
I don't have enough money to get Dad anything good this year.
这星期没给你双倍零用钱？
Well, didn't he double your allowance this week?
有，但这年头4块钱能买什么？
Yeah, but you can't get anything for $4, nowadays.
你懂不懂市道？
Where you been?
不是价钱的问题
Honey, it's not how much you spend.
这个跟麦克，凯罗说吧
Tell that to Mike and Carol.
本.
Look, Ben...
我买不起他一直想要的奔驰450SL.
I can't afford to get your father that Mercedes 450SL...
所以就送他一根钓鱼竿
he's always wanted. So I'm getting him a nice fishing rod...
他也会喜欢，因为他知道我爱他
and he knows I love him, so he'll love it.
希望是吧
I hope.
对了!
I know!
4块钱买蚯蚓送给他
For $4, you can get him some worms.
好主意
Get real, Mom.
我宁愿、送我做的烟灰缸
I might as well just give him the stupid ashtray I made.
那很好，代表了你的心意
Well, that would be fine, punk, as long as it comes from your heart.
形状就是一颗心
It looks like my heart.
本，爸爸没有要你.
Ben, your father is not expecting...
-送什么贵重的礼物 -是吗？
- a big expensive gift from you. - He isn't?
是的
No.
送什么也不要紧
He doesn't care what you get him.
唉
Great.
新婚之夜.
On the wedding night...
新人要意识到.
it is very important to recognize that the couple...
沟通的重要性
must communicate their desires...
书不打开是读不了的
and to understand that you cannot read a closed book.
阁下多少次在火鸡面前.
How often have you sat down to carve a turkey...
因为刀子钝而束手无策？
and found yourself with a dull knife?
-没有一次 -相信主
- Never. - Trust in the Lord...
他会照顾你的所有需要
and all of your needs will be taken care of, for...
祈祷的力量
The power of prayer.
需要上帝帮忙.
Be not afraid to get down on your knees...
别怕，跪下祈祷吧
and ask God for anything.
他会满足你的
He shall provide.
-上帝.. -你在干什么？
- Hello, God? - What are you doing?
我在为钱而祈祷
I happen to be praying for money.
祈祷是不能发财的，我试过了
Ben, you can't pray for money. Believe me, I've tried.
你真以为上帝会给你一张支票？
You actually think God's gonna send you a check or something?
阿门
Amen.
-捐钱给穷人？ -谢谢
- Money for the needy? - Thanks!
-小流氓，还给我 -我就是穷人
- Give me that, you little bandit! - But I'm needy.
我是来收钱的，不是送钱
I'm not giving money away. I'm collecting it.
放聪明点
Wise up.
还以为你的祈祷灵验了
For a minute there, I thought you were onto something.
我需要钱!
But I need money!
-去赌吧 -这是生死存亡的问题
- Join the club. - But this is life or death.
-谁的？ -我的
- Whose? - Mine.
-我很忙 -麦克
- I'm busy. - Mike!
好吧，本
Okay, okay. All right, look, Ben.
你拿着这个挨家逐户去讨钱
I want you to take this can and go from house to house.
瞧你的可怜样，肯定会发财
With your pathetic look, you'll probably make a fortune.
谢谢，麦克!
Thanks, Mike!
谢谢，上帝
And thank you, God.
谢谢，我可没上当
Thanks. You guys didn't fool me.
我就知道你们都记得
I knew all along you remembered.
-记得什么？ -瞧这蛋糕
- Remembered what? - Look at this cake.
-真是.. -熊熊大火
- This is... - It's a raging inferno.
-吹蜡烛! -对
- Blow out the candles! - Yeah.
-我等不了了 -好吧
- I'm burning up in here, Dad. - All right.
我许个愿、望
I know what to wish for.
这老头还真行
Well, not bad for an old geezer.
愿、望没实现，你还在
Well, the wish didn't work. You're still here.
爸爸，先打开好的
Here, Dad. Open the good one first.
谢谢，凯罗
Yeah, thanks, Carol.
-大家真是的 -真幼稚
- Hey, guys. - How juvenile.
凯罗，别让他失望了
Carol, now why do you want to disappoint the man?
这把年纪受不了打击
I mean, at his age, he can't take much of that.
这下决定了
That settles it.
-先看凯罗的礼物 -你一点也不了解.
- I'll open Carol's first. - You know, you can be so insensitive...
长者们的感情
about the problems of older people.
本，你的礼物呢？
Ben, what did you get me?
-最好的应该最后拆 -随便拆一份吧
- The best should be last. - Well, will you just open something?
越长越优先
And the longest shall be first.
好吧，你们先等我打开妈妈的礼物
All right, you guys can all wait while I open something from your mom.
谢谢你
Thank you, dear.
我改变主意了，下个轮到你
No, I changed my mind, Carol. You go next.
不行，到你
No way. You go next.
既然你坚持.
If you insist.
瞧瞧
Yes, look at that.
-喜欢吗？ -很喜欢
- Do you like it? - Honey, I love it.
-可以退货 -不
- I can take it back. - No.
这好极了 钓到每一条鱼我都会想起你
No, this is perfect. Every time I kill a fish, I'll think of you.
杰森，你太好了
Jason, that's so sweet.
爸爸，凯罗让你接着拆她的礼物
Here, Dad, Carol wants you to open my gift, next.
拆吧，你会开怀大笑的
Go ahead, Dad. You could use a good laugh.
是鞋子？
It's shoes, isn't it?
-太好笑了 -谢谢本
- That's funny, Dad. - Thank you, Ben.
瞧!“六零年代巨星”
Look at this! "Superstars of the '60s."
“重温60年代的精神兴欢乐”
"Relive the triumphs, the joy, the spirit of the '60s."
里面所有歌手都因为吸毒死了
Yes. See, everybody on this album died of a drug overdose.
妙极了
Groovy.
-说明他很欣赏 -这是什么？
- "Groovy." That means he likes it. - Okay, what's this?
希望你喜欢.
I wanted to get you something...
这对你和作为心理医师都有作用
that you could enjoy both as a person and as a psychiatrist.
谢谢，我两个身份都会喜欢的
Well, thank you. I'm sure that both of me will love it.
这是.
And it is...
两张百老汇歌剧的门票
two tickets to the off-Broadway production of Nuts.
太好了
That's so great.
轮到我了
Okay, my turn.
对，看看你给我什么
Ben. Yeah, let's see what you got me.
请看!
Ta-da!
你自己包装的？
Wow, you wrap this yourself?
店里包装的
I had it done.
真可爱，把钱都花在包装上了
How sweet. He spent all his money on wrapping.
看看里面是什么
Let's see what we got in here, Ben.
哇，本.
Wow, Ben...
太棒了
this is fabulous.
-我真说不出话了 -我也是
- Maggie, I don't know what to say. - Neither do I.
-这礼物兴我无关 -当然了，兴你无关
- I had nothing to do with this. - Oh, sure, you had nothing to do with it.
真的
Jason, I didn't.
本.
Ben...
这是全自动相机
It does everything all by itself.
白痴也能用
Even an idiot could work it.
-这是哪来的？ -牛斯顿照相馆
- Ben, where'd you get this? - At Newstrom's Camera Store.
满300块送皮套一个
They throw in a leather case every time you spend over $300.
我倒想问问.
All right, I gotta ask.
你们给他的零用钱究竟有多少？
What kind of allowance are you giving this kid, anyway?
-本，钱哪来的？ -洗耳恭听
- Ben, where did you get the money? - Yeah, I'm interested.
我需要钱
Well, see, I needed money.
所以我到邻居那里募捐
So I went around to all our neighbors' houses and asked for money for the needy.
本.西弗，这主意是怎么想出来的？
Benjamin Seaver, where did you ever get an idea like that?
上帝和麦克告诉我的
From God and Mike.
-麦克! -麦克!
- Mike! - Mike!
爸，很明显这里面有误会
So as you can see, Dad, what we have here is just a simple little mix-up.
本太小了，不知道我在开玩笑
Now, young Ben didn't realize that I was only joking...
这事你肯定能理解
but I'm sure that you can see how that could happen...
因为你是个职业精神病医师
particularly since you are a trained psychiatrist...
补充一句，非常优秀的医师
and, may I add, a damn good one.
睁眼说瞎话也能做到？
How do you do that with a straight face?
这是天赋
It's a gift.
这也许能骗爸爸.
Okay, that junk may work on Dad...
但妈妈可是污水废物的专家
but Mom knows raw sewage when she sees it.
凯罗，我是她的大儿子，当然疼爱有加
Carol, I am her firstborn. You might say the woman is putty in my hands.
Oh?
你怎么能说这种话!
But don't say that to me, because that woman...
她是我母亲，我敬爱她!
is my mother and I respect her.
本，你把我搞糊涂了
I'm confused, Ben. I don't get it.
你怎么能挨门逐户撒谎.
I do not understand how you can go door to door, lie to people...
骗取人们的善款.
take their money in the name of charity...
一点也不知悔改
and not have it occur to you that what you were doing was wrong.
可效果比想象中要好
It did seem too good to be true.
怎能干这种蠢事？
How could you act so stupidly?
差点忘了，是麦克的主意
I forgot. You got the idea from Mike.
这相机可是自动卷片的
Did I mention that the camera is self-winding?
-本 -还能自动对焦
- Ben. - And automatic focus?
是吗？
Really?
我一直想送你一份真正的礼物
Well, for once I wanted to get you a real gift.
我感谢你的好意
Well, I know that and I appreciate it...
但你对别人的爱.
and I thank you for the thought, but you don't show somebody...
并不是用金钱来衡量的
how much you love them by how much you spend on them...
除非你老婆是电视明星
unless you're married to Pia Zadora.
-什么？ -没什么
- Huh? - Nothing.
这事该怎么办？
So what do we do about this?
你问我？
You're asking me?
我要你自己想出惩罚的办法.
I think that I'd like to see if you can come up with your own punishment...
好让你明白做错了什么
just to make sure you realize how serious this is.
我？自由选择？
Me? I get to pick whatever I want?
我做最后决定
I get to vote on it.
某些孩子也许会认为这是受罪.
Well, some kids would say that they've suffered enough...
但我不会
but not me.
我这星期会每天9点上床睡觉
I say that every night this week, I should be sent to bed at...
9:00.
本，你本来就是9点睡的
That is your bedtime, Ben.
是啊
Oh, yeah.
要么罚我25岁才能拿驾照
Okay, then, I don't get my driver's license until I'm 25.
-算了，惩罚还是我决定吧 -26岁？
- Forget it. I'll decide your punishment. - 26?
难道你就压根儿没想到.
And it never occurred to you, not even for a second...
本会把你的话当真吗？
that Ben might take you seriously?
谁会把我的话当真啊？
No. Nobody takes me seriously.
这话有道理
He does have a point.
-回房间去 -为什么？
- Carol, go to your room. - Why, Mom?
因为这是命令
Because I said so, young lady.
那就失陪了
Well, excuse me, then.
妈，干得好
Good move, Mom.
是吗？
Can it, Mike.
本把你这位大哥哥.
Now don't you know that Ben looks up to you...
当作榜样看待
his big brother, as an example?
胡说
Get out of here.
我也以为不可能
Look, I don't like it any more than you do...
但你没看到他在学你说话.
but don't you see the way he tries to talk like you...
学你走路，跳舞，任何事情吗？
walk like you, dance like you, do everything like you?
天哪!要让他改邪归正
Oh, my God! Somebody should set this kid straight.
太晚了，他崇拜你
Too late. He worships you.
告诉他我是社会渣滓
Can't we tell him I'm scum or something?
说了他会更热衷
I did. It only made him more interested.
-这个负担我可受不了 -麦克，责无旁贷
- I'm not sure I can live with this burden. - Well, you're stuck with it, Michael...
为了让你记住这点，下个月的零用钱.
and just so you don't forget it, you'll be donating your allowance...
你要捐出来
for the next month to charity.
妈，我做了天大的错事吗？
But, Mom, you're acting like I did something really wrong here.
确实是
I did, didn't I?
好了，本已经承认了错误
Okay, I think Ben understands what he did...
-惩罚我们也决定好了 -我们？
- and we've decided on his punishment. - We?
-首先是退回相机 -好的
- First, we'll be returning the camera. - Good.
-然后退掉所有钱 -好的
- Then we will give back all the money. - Good.
挨家逐户地去还 让本告诉大家他撒谎了
By going house to house, so that Ben can tell everyone he lied.
-杰森 -穿大衣
- Jason. - Okay, get your coat.
-现在去？ -当然了
- You're doing this now? - Absolutely.
-天都黑了 -又怎样？
- But it's almost dark. - So?
我知道他应当受罚
Jason, I know he needs to be punished...
解释的事我去就好
but what if I explain it to the neighbors?
不，他需要吸取教训
No, I think that he's got to understand his own responsibility here.
他还是个小孩子
But, Jason, he's our baby.
-小傻瓜 -9岁半
- A little tyke. - Nine-and-a-half.
我能懂什么？
What do I know?
麦姬，咱的“小傻瓜”.
Maggie, our "little tyke"...
犯的是严重罪行
has committed a felony.
本，别忘了戴手套
Don't forget your mittens, Ben.
“灰尘不能扫到地毯下面就完了”
"Raw sewage cannot simply be swept under the rug."
-不 -妈？
- No. - Mom?
凯罗？
Yes, Carol?
9点了
It's 9:00.
知道了，我也在担心他们
I know, honey. I'm worried about them, too.
我可以出房间了吗？
Can I come out of my room now?
当然了宝贝，快下来
Oh, my God. Sure, honey. Come on down.
对不起，把你关在房间里了
Sweetheart, I'm sorry I sent you to your room.
这太不公道了
That was very unfair of me.
确实是
Yes, it was.
告诉你一个小秘密
Well, let me tell you a little secret...
从来没告诉过你们的
and this is something I've never told you kids before.
什么？
Yeah?
我..还是这样说吧
I'm... Well, I should just say it.
我并不完美
I'm not perfect.
秘密是什么？
Yeah, so what's the secret?
妈妈
Mom. Mom.
我给你准备了伯爵柠檬茶
I've prepared a lovely cup of Earl Grey tea for you with lemon...
还有一块热了的松饼
and an English muffin, lightly toasted.
谢谢你，真是无微不至
Why, thank you, Michael. That was very thoughtful of you.
不过下个月的零用钱还是要捐
Oh, and by the way, it is still a month's allowance...
我很欣赏你的做法
but I like your style.
杰森
- Jason. - Shh!
他睡了？
Is he asleep?
松饼上还加了奶酪
Did I mention that there was cheese on that muffin?
钱还给你
Here's your money back.
对不起我骗你是募捐
I'm sorry I lied about the charity.
好了，儿子，咱回家了
- It's okay, Son. We're home now. - Oh.
-你今晚真让我自豪 -谢谢
- I'm proud of what you did tonight. - Thanks.
得到教训了吗？
Think you learned a lesson?
上帝再给我主意的话，先跟你商量
When God gives me an idea, to check with you first.
还有呢？
Anything else?
爱某个人不必花很多的钱
If you love somebody, you don't have to spend a lot on 'em.
说得对
That's right.
-晚安 -晚安
- Good night, punk. - Good night.
-爸爸？ -什么事？
- Dad? - Yeah?
生日快乐
Happy birthday.
本，这.
Ben, it's...
烟灰缸
An ashtray.
我知道
Yeah, I know.
我要说的是.
What I was going to say was...
这是今年最好的生日礼物
it's the best birthday present I've gotten all year.
但你不抽烟
But you don't even smoke.
我有些病人抽
No, but some of my patients do.
有些想戒掉
Some of them want to quit.
这烟灰缸能帮他们戒烟
I think your ashtray just might do the trick.
这真是个烟灰缸!
Is this an ashtray, or what?
烟蒂可以塞到主动脉里
Look, you stick your butt right in the aorta.
你对本惩罚得对
Jason, you were right about the punishment.
对不起，我当时心软了
I'm sorry I went soft on you.
-没什么，其实我也不忍心 -是吗？
- Well, that's okay. I kinda like you soft. - You do?
其实让你唱红脸也是好事情
Well, actually, it was pretty nice having you be the bad cop, for a change.
是吗？
Really?
因为严厉的你好不性感!
You're very sexy when you're strict.
你!给我回房间!
Well, in that case, go to your room, young lady.
[zeroxia@gmail.com] 2006.04.01